Come on, Alejandro!
It is my turn!
Let me see.
Freedom! Freedom! Freedom!
Hey! What are you doing
cutting holes in my wagon?
I am sorry. Señor Lopez.
We were just waiting for Zorro.
Go home, muchachos.
Do you think he is really
going to come, Señor Lopez?
Someone thinks he will.
Joaquin, Alejandro,
once I carved coffins
for your mother and father.
I would hate to carve one for you.
Now, go!
Alejandro, Joaquin...
This no place for you.
Now get back to the mission.
Come on!
Don Montero, for the love of god,
why are you still here?
Now, now, Don Luiz.
Calm, calm.
Santa Anna's men are three miles
from the town.
You have to go, sir.
Now.
The government of Spain would like
to thank you for your devoted service.
This land is the property
of the Spanish government.
And in two hours' time it will be the
property of the Mexican government...
unless I hand them over to you.
I am well acquainted
with Santa Anna.
He will realize that the dons
will be dutiful taxpayers...
and he will respect your claims.
The rest of Alta California I have
divided up equally among the other dons.
I trust that you will make sure
that all of them receive their grants.
Get the children
out of the plaza immediately.
The children should never
have to see the things we do.
I want to see!
Put me down.
Zorro?
I saw him.
I saw Zorro. Come here.
Who are these men that you would
risk your life to have them killed?
Who are they?
No idea!
Three peasants pulled
at random from the crowd.
Where is he?
Go.
Come on.
My thanks to you gentlemen.
Now, if you will excuse me,
I'm missing my own party.
Kill him!
You would murder three innocent men
just to capture me?
I would murder a hundred innocent men
if it meant killing you.
Three men, three-cuts.
A small memento of Mexico, Rafael...
to remind you not to return.
Tornado, my old friend,
you're getting too old for this.
Yes, me too.
Is she warm enough?
I always put on an
extra blanket for you, Señor.
But the good prince
was not afraid of the evil king.
He raced across the drawbridge,
fighting off a hundred guards.
And then, looking very handsome
and dashing in the late afternoon sun...
he leapt onto the balcony...
and thrust his enchanted sword
under the king's chin.
"You would kill three innocent men,"
he demanded, "just to capture me?"
"Yes. "
Then suddenly, lightning flashed and
a mighty thunder shocked the wasted land.
And the evil king glared
at the good prince and said--
Something very forgettable.
And the good prince?
What did he do?
Well, he leapt from the balcony onto
his faithful old steed Tornado and...
raced home to
his beautiful wife Esperanza...
and to his little child, Elena...
never to do anything so foolish
or dangerous again.
She loves to hear your stories.
Oh, It's only
the sound of my voice.
One day she'll have
no time for them.
I never tire of them.
Why should she?
Esperanza...
- She already has your strength.
- Uh-huh
Today she broke the little clay horse
you made for her.
Diego...
It's just a scratch.
It's all right.
- Diego. you promised me.
- I know.
No more nights waiting up,
praying you'll come home alive.
The Spaniards are going home.
Today is Zorro's last ride.
From now on we'll grow old together
with our five children.
Five?
Yeah.
Not enough?
I love you.
Doña de la Vega,
still as beautiful as ever.
Don Rafael, what an honour!
The governor in my home.
You will stay for dinner,
of course.
I have come to apologize,
Esperanza.
I'm sorry that I could not
protect this country...
from the peasants
who have overrun it.
I'm sorry that
I couldn't make you love me.
And I'm sorry that I have
to leave you without a husband.
Arrest him.
Blood never lies...
Zorro.
You're a traitor to your country
and your class.
Take him away.
Wait!
No!
I would never have let
any harm come to her.
She was never yours
to protect.
Elena...
I want you to live...
with the knowledge
you have lost everything you hold dear.
I want you to suffer
as I have suffered...
knowing that your child
should have been mine.
Elena!
Let me hold her.
Let me hold her!
Rafael!
She has her mother's eyes.
Rafael...
You'll never be rid of me!
Rafael!
¶ Caught the bandits, plain to see ¶
¶ They're tough and they're mean
But don't scare me ¶
¶ Stayed on their track
Bringing them back ¶
¶ So pay the bounty now to me ¶
¶ 'Cause ¶
¶ Nobody's tough as Jack
Nobody's tough as Jack ¶
Now you're gettin' there.
Like I done told ya,
Singin' can lighten your terrible load.
Hey, hey, hey!
Come one! come all!
For the fright of your life!
See the notorious Murrieta brothers.
Robbers! Horse thieves!
Bandits! people of
the worst sort! Hey!
Gather around!
Garcia.
It's the Murrieta brothers.
Get over here.
you mangy trash.
May I, friend?
These men are now in the custody
of Corporal Armando Garcia...
and we will take them
the rest of the way.
And you can claim your bounty
in Tlaxco.
Yeah, when bulls
start wearing' bloomers.
- How much are we worth?
- Get out.
All figured out...
about 200 pesos.
200 pesos? That's it?
After all the payrolls we've robbed?
A lousy 200 pesos apiece!
That's all we're worth?
- We're wasting time.
- That's 200 pesos for the both of ya.
What?
Are you crazy?
Don't take it, Jack!
Back out there!
Touch my brother again,
and I'll kill you.
Yes, he will.
Hey, I thought you were tied up.
That's because you're stupid.
Drop it! Drop it!
Hey!
They got a strongbox
on the wagon.
We know. That's why we came.
Lousy 200 pesos.
That cheats.
It is a fact, that I, the legendary
Three-Fingered Jack, ain't even mentioned.
I ain't even mentioned.
And ain't I the one that figured to
kidnap the mayor from his own outhouse?
I tell you,
I am the holy guts of this gang.
Without me,
the whole dang opera falls apart.
Amigos, adiós.
- Come on. Come on.
- Go! Go!
- Joaquin, Joaquin! Come on, come on.
- Go! Go.
Come on! Get up! Get up!
Go.
I want you to know...
I consider this an honor.
Bury the body.
Bag the head.
Of course
I have feelings for you.
Yes. Yes.
But quick. Hide in the barn.
He's coming.
What do you want?
Please! Don't touch me!
Who are you?
Don Rafael!
Listen to me.
If any one of you is
or ever was that masked man...
all dressed in black
known as Zorro...
Reveal himself now.
I am Zorro!
They took my mask.
My sword, my horse!
- Silence!
You old fool!
I am Zorro!
I am the man you want!
- I am the original!
- Liar!
- The first!
- I am the root!
- Anyone can see you are too tall!
I am the first!
I am Zorro!
Get him out of here
before he starts to stink.
Did you find him?
He's dead.
Back to the boat. I need some sleep
before landing tomorrow.
The governor has returned!
Luiz.
Welcome home, Rafael.
It has been too long.
Too long, my friend.
You said once
you favored me above all.
Consider this a fool's apology
for ever doubting you.
Come.
A crowd has gathered to greet you.
- Don Pedro.
- Don Rafael, welcome.
- You're looking well.
- Thank you.
- Don Hector.
- Welcome back, sir.
Don Julio.
Gentlemen.
Please! please!
I know that you are not
really happy to see me.
So let us all stop pretending,
shall we?
You think I don't know
that you've been paid,
even threatened to come out
in the hot sun and greet me?
I understand exactly how you feel.
Why should you care about
any of your leaders, past or present?
What did they ever do for you?
The Spaniards oppressed you.
The Mexicans ignored you.
And the dons?
Well, the dons, the dons.
The dons seem merely content
to cheat and lie to you.
In fact, I put it to you.
Who in your entire history
has ever helped you?
Zorro!
Zorro fought for the people.
Ah, yes, Zorro.
Where is he now, Padre...
your masked friend?
Unless I'm mistaken,
he hasn't shown himself in 20 years.
Twenty years!
People of California...
The time has come to take
our destiny into our own hands...
Not as Spaniards,
not as Mexicans...
but as Californians!
I stand here before you today
with no mask...
only a pledge...
a solemn pledge
that I will never abandon you.
And you have my word,
the word of Rafael Montero...
that I will do everything
within my power to help you fight...
for a free and
independent California!
Father!
Gentlemen, allow me
to introduce my daughter, Elena.
Thank you.
Can anyone tell me what this flower is?
I knows this scent.
Señor, Señorita. It’s called Romania,
(Correct name: Romneya)
but it only grows in California.
And I believe this is
your first visit to our shores.
Yes.
Hey, hey...
More whiskey...
or whatever you call this.
I don't want to see
the bottom of this glass, huh?
Money first.
Hey, hey, hey! Wait, wait, wait!
- What about this?
- Silver!
Of course, silver.
The finest.
Where did you get that?
It’s none of your business.
Where did you get it?
It was my brother's.
He's dead.
I'm sorry.
You're sorry?
Why should you be sorry?
You should not trade something like that
for a mere glass of whiskey.
Why not?
You think I could get two?
Who's that?
That's the man
who killed my brother.
You're drunk and angry, in no condition
to fight a professional soldier.
Get out of my way, you old man.
Would you care to try again?
You're welcome.
For what?
For saving your life.
- I would have killed him.
- No, not today.
He is trained to kill.
You seem trained to drink.
Yes, my friend, you would have fought
very bravely and died very quickly.
Who, then, would avenge
your brother?
I would have found a way.
I've never lost a fight.
Except to a crippled old man,
just now.
What is your name?
- Alejandro.
You know, there is a saying,
a very old saying.
"When the pupil is ready,
the master will appear."
Have you want to kill this man,
I can help you.
I can teach you how,
how to move, how to think...
how to take your revenge with honor
and live to celebrate it.
But it will take dedication.
It will take time.
Why are you so eager to help me?
Because once, a long time ago...
You did the same for me.
I can't believe it.
I never thought that one day...
I would be standing
in the lair of the fox...
in the lair of Zorro.
Yeah...
this place was devoted
to the training of Zorro.
Where were you all these years?
I thought you were dead.
I was dead,
and we will leave it at that.
I remember the last time
I saw you in the square...
fighting a hundred men.
- A hundred men?
- I do not forget.
You were the greatest swordsman
who ever lived. Yes.
Rafael Montero was
the governor of California, then.
Do you remember him?
What?
Rafael Montero.
Do you remember him?
Yes. His soldiers killed many...
and...
he was
the sworn enemy of Zorro.
That's you.
Montero's come back.
Good. Then you can kill him.
No, there are complications.
Too many complications for me to ignore.
What complications?
I can see we're not
gonna spend much time talking.
Montero has some plan,
some design for California.
Otherwise, he would not have retained
the services of your Captain Love.
We must find out
what that design is.
And then what?
Oh, If you are ready...
We will both tempt our fates.
Let's go, then!
Do you know how
to use that thing?
Yes.
The pointy end
goes into the other man.
Yeah.
This is going
to take a lot of work.
This is called a training circle.
a master's wheel.
This circle will be your world,
your whole life.
Till I tell you otherwise,
there is nothing outside of it.
- Capitan Love is out...
- There is nothing... outside of it.
Captain Love does not exist
until I say he exists.
As your skill
with a sword improves...
you will progress
to a smaller circle.
With each new circle,
your world contracts...
Bringing you that much closer to your adversary,
that much closer to your to retribution.
I like that part.
Shall we?
Slow!
Attack slowly.
Attack! Slow! Again!
Slow! Let's try and...
Slow, like...
Good.
- That is good.
- Thank you.
Attack.
Good!
Time for a drink.
Perfect. Do it again.
One, five, three!
Six, four, two!
And lunge!
Over-lunged!
Lesson number one:
Never attack in anger.
Lesson number two?
Come with me.
What?
So, what is lesson number three?
To get to lesson number four.
Again?
Whoa. Whoa.
Black Andalusian.
Magnificent.
Looks like your old horse,
Tornado.
Quiet. Quiet.
Damn horse!
What are you doing, huh?
What are you doing?!
I'll see you tonight.
Zorro... you look better than ever.
Be careful, Señorita.
There are dangerous men about.
Well...
if you see any,
be sure to point them out.
Everybody's in!
Don't worry, then.
Listen.
I'm going to give you
the great honor...
of being my horse.
We are like one spirit.
Damn it! Damn it, stop!
Go! Go, go, go!
Get him!
Kill him.
Zorro!
The legend has returned!
Don't yell.
I need sanctuary, Father.
You don't know me, so...
Zorro?
Of course I know you.
Zorro, is it really you? I must say, the years
have been far kinder to you than to me.
I'm sorry. I have no time
to talk now.
Father, please, hide me.
Come.
It’s just like the old days.
Padre, is that you?
Padre, is everything all right? It sounds
like there is a battle going on out there.
Don't worry, my dear.
You are safe
in the house of the Lord.
Of course, Padre.
Forgive me, Father,
for I have sinned.
It has been three days
since my last confession.
Three days?
It has been three days
since my last confession.
Three days?
How many sins could you have
committed in three days?
Come back when you have
more time, please.
Excuse me?
Listen, Señorita...
Continue, please...
go on.
I have broken
the fourth commandment, Padre.
- You killed somebody?
- No, that is not the fourth commandment.
Of course not.
You... you...
In what way did you break
the most sacred...
of commandments?
I dishonored my father.
That is not so bad.
Maybe your father deserved it.
What did you say?
I said, tell me more, my child.
Well, I try to behave properly...
the way my father
would like me to...
but I'm afraid
my heart is too wild.
- Too wild?
- Yes.
Could you be
a little more specific about that?
I had impure thoughts about a man.
I did. I think he was a bandit or
something. He wore a black mask.
He had... a deep voice?
Yes.
Ruggedly handsome?
I do not know.
His face was half-covered.
But something in his eyes
captured me.
Captured you.
I felt warm and feverish.
Lustful?
Yes. Lustful.
Forgive me.
I forgive you.
Look over there,
by the altar!
Go the other way.
He has to be here.
Search everything.
The chapel, the loft,
the rectory, all of it.
This is a house of God.
Don't worry, Padre.
We'll be gone by the time he gets back.
Señorita,
you have done nothing wrong.
The only sin would be to deny
what your heart truly feels.
Now, go.
Elena!
- What are you doing here?
- I was confessing.
- Confessing?
- Yes.
To whom?
The priest is here.
Stand back, Elena.
Please.
Out of respect for Miss Montero...
I'll deal with you later.
Horse! Come here!
Blackie! Thunder!
Storm! Stupido!
Get over here now!
I warn you.
I'll get another horse.
So...
what do you think?
Sir. Sir.
I got the black stallion.
I carved a "Z" in the...
Don Diego, the people will be
speaking the name of Zorro again.
You think stealing a horse and scratching marks on the wall
makes you worthy enough to wear that mask?
Be careful.
You're a thief, Alejandro.
A pitiful clown.
Zorro was a servant of the people.
He was not a seeker of fame like you.
A buffoon.
Zorro did what was needed.
And now he's needed again.
I didn't ask for your help
in the cantina...
but I came here
to learn how to fight like you...
to have your strength,
your courage.
Now, when I try to use them,
you slap me down?
Let me tell you something, I am tired
of all your training, your lecturing,
tired of waiting for you
to tell me I am ready.
I have my own scores to settle...
a new life to find.
I thought I could do it here...
but I was wrong.
Alejandro!
En garde!
Choose your weapon.
Montero has invited
every don in California...
to a banquet at his hacienda.
If you want to be of service,
you can join them as a spy.
I think I do not understand, sir.
You have passion, Alejandro,
and your skill is growing...
but to enter Montero's world
I must give you something...
which is completely
beyond your reach.
Oh, yes?
And what is that?
Charm.
Convince Montero
that you're a gentleman of stature...
and he will let you
into his circle.
Me?
A gentleman?
This is going to take a lot of work.
Yes.
Look at me.
I Look like a butterfly.
This is the most stupid thing
I've ever done.
I doubt that.
- We'll never get away with this.
- Yes, we will.
A nobleman is nothing but a man
who says one thing...
and thinks another.
What if Montero realizes who you are?
Montero thinks of himself
as a true nobleman.
He will never Look a servant
in the eye.
Listen to me.
Listen to me!
The most important thing of all...
Do not let the dons
leave the table without you.
- Yes.
- Good.
And good luck tonight.
Thank you.
Stand up straight.
Charm.
Don Rafael Montero?
Good evening.
l am Don Alejandro
del Castillo y Garcia.
Formal greeting
of the Spanish court.
I've not seen that in years.
My father was very strict
in matter of etiquette.
Who is your father?
Don Bartolo del Castillo.
I have heard of Don Bartolo, but I've
never had a pleasure to meet him.
I arrived last week from Spain...
by way of Paris, Lisbon
and San Francisco.
I am inspecting
my family's holdings.
Queen Isabella of Spain
has been very generous to us.
Very impressive.
What brings you to my door?
When I heard you were
back in California...
I knew I must introduce myself.
Her Royal Highness
speaks very highly of you.
Really?
I was under the impression I was
out of favor with the Spanish court...
Since California was lost to Mexico.
Only in certain circles.
Her Majesty knows those unfortunate
events were clearly no fault of yours.
She also told me this province
is still a Land of opportunity...
For a man of vision.
And you are a man of vision?
I am a man in search of a vision.
But my timing is unfortunate.
I have interrupted a party.
Perhaps I could call again?
No, no. It would honor me
for you to join us.
It would honor me to do so, sir.
Please allow me
to introduce my daughter, Elena.
Of course.
Charmed.
I'm afraid I have brought no gift
for the hostess.
But... wait a moment.
- Thank you.
- My pleasure.
Bernardo, pick up your feet.
Señorita. Caballero.
Don Alejandro.
My father and I would like you
to join us at our table.
I would be delighted, Señorita.
Ah, Don Alejandro,
I'm so pleased you could join us.
Gentlemen, allow me to introduce
Don Alejandro del Castillo y Garcia...
Recently returned from Spain.
And this is Captain Harrison Love.
Not a don,
but certainly a kindred spirit.
Are you not the man who was
chasing a Legendary bandit recently?
He was hardly legendary.
So you caught him?
It’s only a matter of time.
Well, the bandit may have escaped...
But the rest of us
will certainly thinks twice...
Before going to confession.
Oh...
Thank you.
With all due respect,
Don Hector, I disagree.
Until these people
are free to govern themselves...
I think we will see many more ''Z''s
carved into walls.
Don Alejandro,
what do you think?
I think...
Sheep will always need a shepherd...
But certainly not
this Zorro creature.
He probably wears the mask to hide
his bald head and unsightly features.
There are some
who would call him heroic.
Heroism.
A romantic illusion.
- Much like nobility.
- Elena, that is enough.
Myself, I would think heroism is
something to aspire to, not sneer at.
All that playing with swords...
shooting guns,
racing around with horses...
gives me a frightful headache.
Such sweaty pursuits are hardly
the work of a gentleman.
And what is?
Climbing in and out of carriages?
No, my dear.
But increasing one's holdings
so as to provide lavish comfort...
for young ladies...
such as yourself.
A woman's grasp of politics.
What can I say?
Well, we're at a party,
aren't we?
Elena...
may I have the honor
of this dance?
I would be glad to.
Yes?... Were you
looking for something?
A sense of the miraculous
in everyday life.
Oh, really. Well, why don't you
try looking someplace else?
The lady and I were trying to dance.
You were trying.
She was succeeding.
Forgive me, Capitan.
A shameless joke at your expense...
And I hope it will not be the last.
Don Rafael wants you
back at his table... now.
Would you care to try
something more robust?
Or do you feel unequal
to the task?
No, on the contrary,
Don Alejandro.
I think only of your distaste
for perspiration.
Maestro.
Well, that is the way
they are dancing in Madrid these days.
Excuse me, Don Rafael.
I need to catch my breath.
Your daughter is
a very spirited dancer.
"Spirited". Thank you
for putting it so delicately.
I apologize if you were offended.
Oh, no, no, no, no.
Completely unnecessary, I assure you.
She is young and impulsive.
But her beauty is beyond compare...
And she has her father's
commanding presence.
Don Rafael!
As an advisor to Her Royal Highness
in matters of finance...
It would be my pleasure
to introduce you both at court.
Join us in the courtyard. There's
something I'd Like to share with you.
What is that?
A vision.
Fellow dons of California...
All of us here can recall the golden
years when we ruled this country.
We commanded respect as nobleman,
and we amassed a great deal of wealth...
but there was something
we never achieved.
We never determined
our own destiny.
Well, the time has come.
Time to claim what always
should have been ours.
My friends...
I give you the independent
Republic of California.
Don Rafael...
every man here
owes you something.
The land you gave us
made us all wealthy men.
However,
we must question your motives.
The day you arrived on the beach,
you made us all look like fools.
That is absurd, Don Pedro.
I was merely playing to the crowd.
And what are you doing now
if not "playing to the crowd"?
Now you're inciting us
to raise arms against Santa Anna...
when you know perfectly well
we could never defeat his army.
I was not suggesting
that we fight him for California.
I was suggesting
that we buy it from him.
Santa Anna is waging a very expensive
war with the United States...
and is increasingly short of money.
Even if we all
combined our fortunes...
we could not come up with enough money
to buy this country from Santa Anna.
I have already
brokered a deal with him.
You're living in a dream, Montero.
And why don't we all live
in the same dream together?
Meet me here tomorrow morning,
gentlemen...
for a journey that will open your eyes
and laid all your doubts to rest.
My friends, I give you...
El Dorado!
Technically, of course,
all this gold belongs to Santa Anna...
but fortunately for us, he's
completely unaware of it's existence.
Now, for the deception to work,
all these bars...
have been marked with the Spanish seal
so he'll think they've come from Spain.
You see now, gentlemen?
Is it becoming clearer to you?
Two days from now we will
buy this country from Santa Anna...
And we will buy it with gold
dug from his own land.
Where did you find all these people?
Anywhere we wanted.
Brilliant.
It’s only part of the mining process.
At first we were just picking it up
off the ground, but now we're down blasting.
So, this is the future
of California, huh?
This is my vision, yes.
Up here!
Well, now ain't you
a sight for sore eyes.
Full-grown vultures
walking' around like real folks.
Welcome!
Welcome to hell's outhouse.
They call us
"the disappeared ones. "
But, as you can see,
we ain't exactly disappeared.
- We just been a little hard to find.
- Wait!
You. I know you.
You bet you do, peckerwood.
I'm the legendary
Three-Fingered Jack...
And you are
a bunch of murdering' trash...
Dressed up in fancy,
sweet-smelling' doodads.
Ignore him, gentlemen.
He's a common thief.
Huh! As common as they come.
But I ain't nothing'
compared to you, gentlemen.
I steal gold.
I steal money.
But you,
you steal people's lives.
So damn ya...
and damn the horse that brung ya!
"Peckerwood"?
Is there something amusing to you?
Strange, I'd say.
That's the second time I've shot this man
while he was flying through the air.
Don Alejandro!
I need to speak with you
at the hacienda... alone.
Some other time, perhaps.
Today.
Alone.
Good afternoon, Bernardo.
Good afternoon, Señorita.
Your voice is so calming.
He's high-spirited.
He needs to hear something soothing.
Yes, I understand.
How long have you served
Don Alejandro?
Sometimes it seems interminable.
- I'm sorry. I speak out of place.
- Do not worry, Bernardo.
He will not hear it from me.
Don Alejandro confuses me.
Sometimes he seems so arrogant,
so superior.
And yet the way
that he looks at me and...
the way that he dances with me...
As if he were two
completely different man.
Yes.
You look so much like your mother.
How would you know that?
Well...
I don't see much
of Don Rafael in you.
I know my father wishes
I acted more like her.
She was very proper, my mother.
Always appropriate.
Is that how he describes her?
Yes. But sometimes
I do not believe him.
She was more like you.
Perhaps.
It would be a way
of knowing her.
My ninera once told me...
That the departed
can see you in the moonlight.
So when I was young I used to
sneak out at my window at night...
And ride my horse across Andalusia...
And wave at the sky
so she would know it was me.
How did she die?
Giving birth to me.
My father rarely speaks of her.
I think he finds it too painful.
Yes.
I know what it is like
to losing a loved one.
You?
Yes. A daughter.
Long ago.
When I see you, I remember
what it felt like to be a father.
I'm sure your mother would be
very proud of you, Señorita.
Thank you.
Bernardo, I have to ask you:
Have we ever met before?
No... why would you think that?
I don't know. It’s strange.
Your voice seems
so familiar somehow.
Well, I haven't been to Spain
since before you were born.
Of course.
Well, it's a very pleasant voice.
Thank you.
Good day, Bernardo.
Good day...
Elena.
Did you know that
the Compa Indians of Central Peru...
used to cannibalize their slain enemies
in order to absorb their power?
The eyes, in particular,
were most sought-after.
To be able to see
through the eyes of an enemy...
is a valuable thing.
Where are my manners?
Would you...
Would you care for something to drink?
No?
A different vintage, perhaps.
You're a very sick person,
Capitan Love.
Heads in water jars,
hands in wine pitchers...
must strike you as odd,
I suppose.
Well, for one thing, I think
you ought to fire your housekeeper.
Who is he?
An enemy.
He has a brother out there
who will share the same fate.
I wish you luck.
To your health.
Murrieta's brother or not...
You are more
than you pretend to be.
Maybe someday...
I will see what I look like
through your eyes...
Capitan Love.
Oh, it is beautiful.
Excuse me.
How much does it cost?
It is a gift, she says,
in honor of your mother.
My mother?
She loved your mother.
No, tell her she must be mistaken.
My mother died long ago in Spain.
She says there is
no mistaken the daughter...
of Esperanza and Diego de la Vega.
She says she was your nanny.
She hung flowers on your crib
when you were little.
I'm sorry.
I cannot accept it.
Alejandro...
Alejandro, listen to me.
Can you find your way
back to the mine?
No.
The carriage windows
were all covered.
He didn't even trust
his own dons.
Nor would I.
You must go
to Montero's house tonight...
break into the chest of his study...
find anything that will tell us
what his plans are--
People at the mine are dying...
and... all I can think of is...
Capitan Love.
He will come into your circle
soon enough. You need not chase him.
- I miss my brother, sir.
- Your brother is dead.
We lose the ones we love.
we cannot change it. Put it aside.
How?
How can I do what is needed...
when all I feel is...
hate?
You hide it...
with this.
Santa Anna has agreed to the transfer
at noon, the day after tomorrow...
but he insists we deliver the gold
five miles north of town.
Captain Love?
It’s a safe distance from the mine.
The bars are stamped and ready.
I don't foresee a problem.
Tell him we agree.
You've done well, Luiz.
Very well.
To the independent
Republic of California.
Don Rafael!
Did you send men to the hills?
Doubled the guard at the wall?
Yes, yes, of course.
- After all, if it's only one man...
- It isn't just one man. Damn it.
It’s Zorro.
And he knows about the mine.
Otherwise
he wouldn't be here tonight.
- How could he possibly...
- It doesn't matter how.
You don't seem
to grasp the situation, Captain.
If Santa Anna finds out we've paid him
in gold stolen from his own land...
he will have us butchered,
like cattle.
Do you understand?
Then we should destroy the evidence.
Set explosives, bury the mine.
And the workers?
We destroy all the evidence,
Don Rafael.
No witnesses.
Make sure those papers
are locked up.
Guards!
The much-debated Zorro.
No.
The Legendary Zorro.
Put down your weapons!
Tell them.
Do as he says.
Allow me.
Come.
Stop.
Face the window.
Now, bend down and touch your toes.
Bend over!
Do excuse me,
Capitan Love.
Thank you.
Kill him!
Good morning, Señor.
Good morning, Señorita.
- Give it back.
- What?
Whatever it is you have stolen from
my father, I want it back. Give it to me!
No.
Come on now.
I don't have the time
to give you the proper instruction.
I have had the proper instruction
since I was four.
Not bad.
Not bad at all.
This will make it more difficult.
Señorita--
Don't move.
Do you surrender?
Never.
But I may scream.
I understand.
Sometimes I have that effect.
Excuse me.
Good-bye, Señorita.
What are you doing here?
What happened?
Zorro.
Zorro was here.
I fought him, and he left.
He left!
Did you recognize him?
No...
but he was young and vigorous.
He was very vigorous, Father.
- Vigorous?
- Yes.
Let's go!
Go!
Here.
This is the canyon.
That is where the mine is.
They have...
25, 30 guards at most.
- Nothing that Zorro can't overcome.
- I'm not going with you.
What?
I'm not going with you.
There's something I must do.
It’s a personal matter.
What about the prisoners?
There's nothing more
I can do for them.
You mean nothing you will do.
I gave my life to them.
In return, I lost everything.
My wife was murdered before my eyes,
and my child was stolen...
to be raised by my mortal enemy.
Montero?
Elena.
She's your daughter.
Yes. She was.
So...
You will simply take your revenge.
No, I will take my daughter.
And don't pretend
she means nothing to you.
Well, she does.
But you taught me to see beyond
personal feelings. Remember?
Was that all a lie?
- You're too young to understand.
- To understand what?
Betrayal?
All the work, all the training,
all the wise words, for what?
To smile in the face of my brother's
killer while you make your own plans?
Alejandro, I taught you
everything you need to survive.
Now I must look to my own heart.
Elena is all I have left.
I'm not going to lose her again.
What about California?
What about the people?
They still have Zorro.
I have every inch
of the countryside covered.
If he shows himself...
Are you all right?
- Do you have the map?
- We'll find it.
Is your army ready
to fight Santa Anna's?
No, sir.
Then why are you asking me if I'm
all right. Of course, I'm not all right.
Now I'm really beginning to wonder if you want
this operation to succeed at all, Captain Love.
- Just what are you saying, Don Rafael?
- What I'm saying, Captain...
is that I think my horse
could run this army better than you.
I said I'll find him.
That means I will.
Perhaps I can save you
the trouble.
Go on.
Reach for it, Captain.
Who are you?
I warned you long ago,
Rafael...
that you would never be rid of me.
De la Vega.
Rafael.
You were not the Zorro
I saw last night.
That was your master,
Don Alejandro.
Yes.
But there are many who would
proudly wear the mask of Zorro.
Either way,
it's of little consequence.
Events have been set in motion
that you cannot stop.
I'm not here to stop you.
Call for Elena.
Call her.
Captain...
bring my daughter to me.
Bring her to me!
You cannot imagine, Rafael...
how I have dreamed of this moment.
Night and day, 20 long years.
Really?
I haven't given you
a second thought.
If I die, De la Vega,
the truth dies with me.
We shall see.
Father!
Bernardo, what are you doing?
Tell her, Rafael.
Tell me what?
What is going on?
Tell her who her real father is.
Father, what is he saying?
This...
unfortunate man
lost a daughter once.
It has driven him mad, and now
he seeks to claim you for his own.
Tell her...
how her mother died.
Your daughter is lost,
De la Vega.
You cannot have mine.
De la Vega?
A woman in town, she told me.
Diego de la Vega?
Father?
His name is of no consequence...
I was told my ninera
used to hang something on my crib.
Yes.
She had her hang fresh flowers...
No!
Let us finish it, Rafael.
Let us finish what we started
the night Esperanza died.
Drop your sword...
or I will have no choice
but to have you shot...
even in the presence
of my daughter.
Please.
They were flowers.
Romania.
(Romneya)
Rafael...
She knows.
Water!
Lock them up!
The fuses are burning.
Hurry it up.
Let's go!
Wait here!
Secure the wagon.
Stay alert.
De la Vega.
Rafael.
Only one question.
Really? What is that?
How would you like
your remains displayed?
Now I am free...
- to kill you.
- No!
Drop the sword.
Drop it.
You really think
I would have killed my own child?
Did you miss me?
Elena! Get them out!
"M"...
for Murrieta.
Two men.
One dead!
You're doing well.
Your brother would have
shot himself by now.
Alejandro.
Is it finished?
Yes, Don Diego.
It’s finished.
Not for Zorro.
There will be other days,
other battles to fight.
It is your curse and destiny.
My beautiful Elena.
The world is a strange place.
To have found you at last,
only to lose you again.
You will never lose me...
Father.
Elena...
You are like your mother.
Same eyes.
Same mouth.
Same spirit.
Alejandro.
My child.
And so it was.
Lightning split the sky.
Thunder shook the earth.
Then all was quiet.
The great warrior known as Zorro...
was gone.
The people of the land
gave him a hero's funeral.
The largest anyone had ever seen.
They came from far and wide...
to say farewell
to the brave and noble champion.
But don't worry, little Joaquin.
Whenever great deeds are remembered...
your grandfather will live on.
For there must always,
always be a Zorro.
And someday, when he's needed...
We will see him again...
On his fearsome steed Tornado...
riding like the wind...
his sword blazing in the sun.
Leaping, jumping,
swinging through the air.
Fighting like a lion.
Fighting like a tiger.
Fighting...
As safely as possible.
Is this your idea
of putting the baby to sleep?
Sleep tight, my son.
When I sleep, I will dream
of this dashing rogue Zorro.
But what face shall I give him?
He has been many different men, but...
he has loved you as all of them.
How can I refuse such a man?
Do you know where I might find him?
You know Zorro.
He could be anywhere.
There, there, my darling.